A Guide to the Beverly Willis Architectural Papers, 1954-1998
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- Project Files, 1958-1998 (Map-case 1:1-15:2, Carton 1-49, Box 2-3)
  - Project 0753: San Francisco Ballet Building, 1981 (Map-case 7:1-8, Map-case 16:3-5, Carton 28)
    - Profiles, 2
    - Sections, 16
    - Vicinity Map, 2
    - Project Papers (Carton 28)
      Meeting notes, correspondence, and invoices
  - Project 0754: Yerba Buena Center Flowchart, 1981 (Carton 46)
  - Project 0755: Anderson Residence, San Francisco, California, 1981
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 5
    - Construction Drawings, Set of 10 pages, incomplete
    - Design Sketches, 57 pages
    - Details, 7
    - Presentation Documents, 1 set of 13 pages
  - Project 0757: Capitol Center, 1983 (Carton 1)
    Project papers; include photographs, reference and planning materials, correspondence, transmittals, and project study
  - Project 0758: Anderson Residence, Midland, Texas, 1981 (Map-case 7:10, Carton 28)
    Three books
  - Project 0759: San Francisco Home Health Service Damp Proofing, 1982 (Carton 32)
  - Project 0760: San Francisco Home Health Service Life Safe Systems, 1982 (Carton 32)
  - Project 0761: Adult Day Care Center, San Francisco Home Health and Hospice Center, 1982 (Map-case 7:11, Carton 32)
    Provided design and construction drawings
    - Design Sketch, 1
    - Project Papers (Carton 32)
      Unidentified.
  - Project 0762: 1982 (Carton 32)
  - Project 0764: San Francisco Home Health Service Elevator Replacement, 1983 (Carton 32)
  - Project 0765: Catalyst Financial Corporation, San Francisco, California, 1983 (Map-case 8:1-2)
    Feasibility study
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 4
    - Design Sketch, 61
    - Massing Study, 8
    - Presentation Documents, 1 set of 12 pages
  - Project 0766: Kohlenberg Residence, San Francisco, California, 1983 (Map-case 7:9, Map-case 8:3, Carton 1)
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 3
    - Design Sketch, 24
    - Project Papers (Carton 1)
      Includes sketches (existing, conceptual, and working)
  - Project 0767: Capital Center, 1981 (Carton 30)
    Miscellaneous project papers; include contracts, consultant records, and invoices.
  - Project 0769: Equestrian Center, MountHolyoke College, South Haley, Massachusetts, 1983 (Map-case 8:3, Carton 1)
    Master planning for equestrian center, including center design. Unbuilt (couldn't raise funds).
    - Building Plan, 1
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 30
    - Design Sketch, 6
    - Presentation Drawings, 1 set of 5 pages and 1 loose page; 6 in all
    - Site Plan, 1
    - Specifications, 1 sheet
    - Project Papers (Carton 1)
      Includes details, outline specifications (Q-1), diagram, feasibility study, general correspondence, and reference material
  - Project 0770: Brannan Street Renovation, San Francisco, California, 1983 (Map-case 8:4, Carton 30)
    Project to convert existing warehouse into an office building. Design and construction.
    - Design Sketch, 5
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 5
    - Building plan from survey, 1
    - Elevation and section from survey, 2
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 20 pages
    - Miscellaneous Project Papers (Carton 30)
      Include specifications, invoices, photographs and microfilmed plans.
    - Specifications (Carton 30)
    - Invoices (Carton 30)
    - Photographs and microfilmed plans (Carton 30)
  - Project 0771: Post and Gough Building, San Francisco, California, 1983 (Map-case 8:5-8, Carton 31)
    Design and construction drawing for converting a 1930s warehouse with neo-classical facade and building on top of it an additional seven floors of parking and office space. Unbuilt.
    - Color Study
    - Conceptual Design Drawing
    - Construction drawings, 1 set of 73 pages
      Include axonometric studies.
    - Design Sketches
    - Detail
    - Presentation Documents
    - Presentation Drawing
    - Project Schedule
    - Proportion Studies
    - Specifications and preliminaries (Carton 3 folders)
    - Project Papers (Carton 31)
      Includes meeting minutes, correspondence, sketches, schedules, specifications and preliminaries.
  - Project 0772: Abbey Rents' Retail Building, 1983 (Map-case 8:9)
    Renovation, design, and construction drawings for the Abbey Rents' building conversion into retail shops.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 5 pages
    - Construction Drawings, 19 pages, not a set
    - Design Sketch, 30
    - Project Papers, 1 folder (Carton 31)
    - Photographs and Films, 1 folder (Carton 31)
  - Project 0773: Dixon Residence, St. Helena, California, 1984 (Map-case 8:10, Carton 30)
    - Design Sketch, 16 pages
    - Elevation, 2
    - Roof Plan, 1
    - Plot Plan, 1
    - Presentation Documents, 14 pages, not a set
    - Project Papers (Carton 30)
  - Project 0774: Equestrian Condominiums, Washoe City, Nevada, 1984 (Map-case 8:11, Folder 30)
    Conceptual design of residential condominiums around an equestrian center. Unbuilt.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 4
    - Physical and Slope Analysis, 4
    - Topography Map, 2
      Not generated by Beverly Willis.
    - Project Papers
  - Project 0775: Sacramento Street Wine and Spirits, 1984 (Carton 30)
  - Project 0776: New Front Street, 1984 (Carton 30)
    Two books
  - Project 0778: Ventures IX, Fillmore Street, San Francisco, California, 1984 (Map-case 9:1)
    Provided design and construction drawings for renovation and addition in order to create a mid-rise office building.
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 28 pages
    - Design Sketch, 7
    - Photograph, Copy of photograph of site.
    - Presentation Documents, Set of 4 pages
  - Project 0779: Brannan Street Study, San Francisco, California, 1984 (Map-case 9:2, Carton 5)
    Project entailed executing feasibility study for addition to existing building.
    - Feasibility Study
    - Sketches, 11
    - Project Papers, 2 folders (Carton 5)
  - Project 0781: Markborough Properties, San Francisco, California, 1984 (Map-case 9:3)
    Project entailed conducting massing studies to reconfigure an existing design for a new office tower. Unbuilt.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 12 pages
    - Design Sketches, 3 pages
    - Elevation, 1
    - Scheme Summary, 1
    - Site Map, 1
      A presentation drawing.
  - Project 0782: Laurel Heights Remodel (Carton 32)
    Project papers, including contacts, consultants, and invoices
  - Project 0783: Bulletin Building, Mission Street, San Francisco, California, 1985 (Map-case 9:4, Carton 32)
    Feasibility study for retail uses.
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 13 pages
    - Building Plan
    - Retail Leasing Plan
      Mock-up copy and sample.
    - Miscellaneous Project Papers (Carton 32)
      Include specification, consultants, contracts, and invoices
  - Project 0784: Third and Mission Street, San Francisco, California, 1985 (Map-case 9:5)
    Conceptual massing project. Unbuilt.
    - Design Sketch, 22
  - Project 0785: Alice Arts Center, Oakland, California, 1985 (Map-case 9:6-12, Carton 3-4)
    Renovation design and construction drawings for converting an existing building into an arts center.
    - Construction Drawings, 1 complete set of 56 pages, one reduced photocopies set of 56 pages
    - Correspondence, 2 letters (Carton 4)
    - Design Sketch, 7
    - Elevation, with notes, 1, and transparency overlay
    - Presentation Drawings, 4 pages
    - Project Papers (Carton 3-4)
      Include correspondence, notes, studies, costs, fee negotiations and invoices, product information, original details, OEDE consultant agreement, specifications and details, tenant art groups file, and structural calculations.
  - Project 0786: 812 Mission Street, San Francisco, California (Map-case 9:13-16, Carton 32)
    Lobby, corridors and elevator renovation design and construction drawings.
    - Color Study
    - Construction Drawings, 1 set of 35 pages
    - Design Sketch, 46 pages
    - Photographs, 1 contact sheet
    - Presentation Drawings
  - Project 0787: Yerba Buena Center (Map-case 9:17, Carton 1)
    Project included pen and ink mapping drawings of hotel site.
    - Legal Documents, 32
  - Project 0790: Shown and Sons Winery, 1986 (Map-case 10:1, Carton 1)
    Design, construction drawing, and other project papers for a new, free standing, winery and storage caves utilizing passive energy.
    Extended Description: Behind the form of the winery, the aging sheds and the terrace lie images of the traditions common to wine-making throughout the centuries. Willis transforms these historical images into crisp contemporary form through the use of geometry and the incorporation of natural materials that respond to the agrarian
    In the main building of the winery, the facade of vertical grain redwoods are fitted together like the staves of an oak cask, held rigidly in place by two large steel bands encircling the building under a tern metal roof. The golden mean proportion that governs the scale and relationships of the design encompasses a cylindrical cupola at the winery roof. The warm air of the California day is drawn upward, escaping through the cupola's perimeter vents.
    To maintain the constant temperature required in the aging process, Willis designed the areas as "caves", determining through computer analysis the appropriate thermal mass for passive cooling. Supported by a timed intake fan rather than air conditioning, strict temperature criteria are met with reduced energy consumption.
    - Construction Drawing, 14
    - Design Sketch, 40 pages
    - Elevation, 4
    - Presentation Drawing, 1
    - Site Plan, 3 pages
    - Site Photographs, 7
    - Outline Specifications (Carton 1)
  - Project 0791 (Carton 1)
  - Project 0792: Lorraine Legg Lobby (Carton 1)
  - Project 0794: Pool House Entertainment Center, Yountville, California, 1987 (Map-case 10:2, Folder 33)
    Design, construction drawings and supervision of entertainment center and pool house project.
    Extended Description: In designing a pool house to be located on an old campsite of the Wappa Indians, Willis responded to the owners' desire to preserve a rumored burial mound by reinventing a bit of history. Nomadic gatherers and hunters, the Wappa tribe had left little evidence of their cultural traditions or imagery. Through the use of universal mythical images -- such as the sun, eagle and sky boat -- Willis recreated the spiritual journey of the ancient tribe in stucco bias relief on the pool-house facade and through the design of a memorial sun marker.
    Located beside an existing swimming pool, the pool house was designed to accommodate casual pool-side entertaining as well as the functional necessities of showering and dressing, Willis used the golden section to generate all parts of the building form, modulating the two squares of the floor plan with a trace of the roof to derive three distinct spaces. In the vaulted center section, sliding doors are pocketed into the walls, dissolving the boundaries between pool and house.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 4
    - Construction drawings, One set of 10 pages, one set of 3 pages
    - Design Sketches, 19
    - Site Plan, 1
    - Topography
    - Project Papers (Carton 33)
      Includes correspondence, names, addresses, change orders, specifications, job notes, design reference, construction costs, permits, job-site reports, and details
  - Project 0795: Pat Ellison, ca. 1987 (Carton 1)
  - Project 0796: Schneider Residence, St. Helena, California, 1987 (Map-case 10:3, Carton 33)
    Design and construction drawings for renovation of a two-story house.
    - Conceptual Design Drawings, 7
    - Construction Drawings, Set of 12 pages
    - Design sketches, 5 pages
    - Details and specifications, 2 folders (Carton 33)
    - Project Papers, 1 folder (Carton 33)
      Includes photographs, project papers, specifications and details, contract, consultants, and invoice
    - Photographs, 1 folder (Carton 33)
  - Project 0797: 545 Mission Tower, 1979
  - Project 0798: Pam Hunter's Office, 1987
  - Project 0800: Bay Club at Yerba Buena Gardens, 1987 (Map-case 10:4, Carton 33)
    Conceptual design for free standing building to be used as a fitness center. Unbuilt.
    - Design Sketch, 21
    - Elevation, 4
    - Project Photographs, 2
    - Project Photographs, 2
    - Presentation Drawing, 3
    - Project Flow Chart, 6 pages
    - Project Papers (Carton 33)
      Contract, invoices, and Yerba Buena Gardens Fitness Center Concept
  - Project 0801: World Wildlife Safari Park, 1988 (Map-case 16:6, Carton 33)
    Project papers, including correspondence, research and notes, programs, contract, and invoices
  - Project 0802: Anne Radice Apartment, Washington, D.C., 1987 (Map-case 10:5, Carton 33)
    Designed, developed construction drawings and supervised construction for interior design of apartment.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 3
    - Design Sketches, 4
    - Presentation Documents, Set of 3 pages.
    - Section, 1
    - Project Papers (Carton 33)
      Contract and invoices.
  - Project 0803: San Francisco Opera (Carton 33)
    Project papers, including fee negotiations and expenses, feasibility studies, contract, and invoices
  - Project 0804: Mr. and Mrs. Arthur Rock Residence, San Francisco, California, 1989 (Map-case 10:6, Carton 35)
    Consulting on interior refurbishing.
    - Conceptual Design Drawing, 2 pages
    - Presentation Documents, 9 pages
    - Projects and Invoices
  - Project 0805: Berkshire Festival Theatre, 1989
  - Project 0806: Rutberg Fine Arts Gallery, 1990 (Carton 35)
    Item labeled "Book 2"
  - Project 0807: Manhattan Village Academy High School, New York, New York, 1994-1998 (Map-case 10:7-8, Carton 34)
    Design Architect created innovative small school plan and introduced the Locus clustering concept.
    - Building Plan, 7
    - Construction Drawing, 1 set of 61 pages
    - Design Sketch, 100
    - Elevations, 4 (all southern)
    - Furniture Building Plan, 2
    - Isometric Drawing, 6 pages
    - Presentation Drawing, 9 pages
    - Mechanical and Electrical Specifications, 1 folder (Carton 3)
    - Zip Discs (Carton 34)
      Content unspecified.
    - Project Papers
      Includes correspondence with Korchein and Board of Education, work in progress, computer discs, mechanical and electrical specifications
  - Project 0810: River Run, St. Helena, California, 1983 (Map-case 11:1, Folder 1, 36, and 48)
    Extended Description: The focus of the River Run property consisted of two small knolls nestled side-by-side overlooking the flat valley land and the Napa River. Entered by way of a nineteenth century stone bridge, a working vineyard of Chardonnay grapes surrounds the knolls, the first of which houses the remodeled estate gate house. In the field between the knolls were two barns, one of which Willis remodeled as a stable with full tack room and grooming area.
    The farmhouse, imbued with the image of a Palladian villa, monumentally commands the second knoll along with a renovated guest house and pool. The grand semicircular staircase and the symmetrical facade contrast with the asymmetrical elements of the natural landscaping. The form of the portico recalls the colonnades of early Tuscany, their redwood material exuding a warmth not found in the stone and masonry of their historic counterparts.
    The interior of the house is comprised of four "living centers" -- the public reception and entertainment area, the food preparation and relaxation area, the more private library and study area, and the fully private sleeping and bath areas. Sharing fireplace with the master bedroom, the master bath has a view of the pool that links the guest and main houses.
    - Axonometric Drawing, 1
    - Elevation, 4
    - Section, 2
    - Site Plan, 6 + 1 negative
    - Photographs (credit Peter Aaron)
    - Details and Project Notes, 4 folders (Carton 1)
  - Project 0811: Willis Residence, New York, New York, 1991 (Map-case 11:2)
    Renovation and restoration of a 5-story 1856 brownstone with cellar [townhouse], of approximately 3,500 square feet for a living-working space for Beverly Willis. (The house was remodeled ca. 1955 and the original detailing and many walls were removed at this time.) Budget, $350,000.
    - Construction Drawings, 4
    - Videotape
    - Project 0812: Bridges to Brooklyn High School, New York, New York, 1994 (Map-case 11:3, Carton 35)
      Project to renovate and convert warehouse into school.
    - Construction Drawing, 2 sets, 27 pages. 1 set is a reduced photocopy.
    - Site Survey
    - Project Papers (Carton 35)
      Includes schematic plans, work scope, correspondence, and contractor costs
  - Project 0813: Greenwich Apartment, 1978 (Map-case 11:4)
    - Presentation Drawings, 2
  - Project 0814: Rosita Wall Table, 1992 (Map-case 11:5)
    Design and construction of wall table.
    - Construction Drawing, 1 page
  - Project 0817: Promotional Book, Willis and Associates, ca. 1980 (Carton 8)
    Miscellaneous brochures.
- Beverly Willis Media, 1985, 2 videos (Carton 2)
  This small series is comprised of two promotional videos produced by Beverly Willis Media.
  - "Beverly Willis - Architect," 1985 (Carton 2)
  - "Yerba Buena Gardens," 1985
- Miscellaneous Project Records, 1976-1986 (Carton 36-49)
  This series is comprised of financial records, memos, job notes, letters of transmittal, correspondence, and other financial records. An inventory of file folders for these boxes is available at the repository.
  Not arranged by project number or format.
- CARLA Records, 1972-ca. 1978 (Carton 49-51)
  This series spans the period 1972-1978 and documents the development of CARLA, Computerized Approach to Residential Land Analysis, by Beverly Willis, Eric Tiescholz, and Jochen Eigen. The system enabled architects to use computers to develop site plan design techniques more efficiently.
  It contains computer paper drive tapes of software program versions, a computer-punched paper drive of CARLA original film, flowcharts, videotapes, rough material for CARLA videotape, articles about computer-assisted analysis and mapping systems, computer manuals, and memos. Also included are Jochen Eigen's 1974 notes on interfacing CARLA with a computer mapping program.
- Presentation Documents 1976 (Carton 2, Map-case 15:3, Box 1)
  This series is comprised of paper, photographs, mounted prints, negatives, and mock-ups of Willis projects compiled in 1976.
  - Paper
  - Photographs
  - Negatives
  - Presentation Mock-Ups
  - Photographic Prints n.d., 12 8 x 10 color prints of Willis' work, enlarged from prints and framed with white matte board. (Map-case 15:3)
- Ephemera, 1990, 1 poster (Map-case 15:2)
  Poster from the exhibit, "Risk Factor 16: Going out on a Limb," sponsored by the Art Directors and Artists Club of Sacramento, Sacramento Community Center.